We've got uh a super popular um platform
IDE that that we're going to be talking
about next. Um this is a platform that's
uh that's been in development for uh a
year, just over a year. Uh it's been
available for 4 months. It was so
popular actually that they had to close
off the the the open first. I think you
got 100,000 or so uh usage downloads in
in a short period. Um now though, really
happy to say it's a it's a GA product.
So uh Kira is is fully GA. Um and Al
Harris is the tech lead uh at AWS over
at Kro and he's going to be talking
about how you can use specs as part of
spec driven development to to really
build out those incremental features. So
uh pass it over to Al. Al, over to you.
>> Yeah, thank you.
Uh so first of all, thank you for having
me. Uh and thank you for putting me on
the spot about our sort of rolled back
preview release we did a few months ago.
Uh that was a fun time. My name is Al
like uh like Simon mentioned. Um
principal engineer at Amazon. I'm the
tech lead for Kira. Um I think we have
Renee here today as well speaking, but
he another engineer and I basically
built Kira from the ground up and
launched it publicly I think four four
and a half months ago something like
that at this point. But yeah, GA this
week, which basically means we can take
money in a in a better way now. But uh
other than that, uh I'm here to talk a
little bit more about spectriven
development. So the reason we shipped
Kira was really because we believed that
specri development was going to change
the way we interacted with AI tools and
allowed us to use these tools better. So
quick show hands. Who here's done
something that you would qualify as
specriven development?
Maybe 50/50. So, I'm going to just kind
of flip a coin and say I bet we're not
calling spec driven dev the same thing.
That's kind of the starting point. Uh,
everybody has their own definition right
now. Spec is an overloaded term. But,
um, I am going to slightly disagree with
what guy said earlier this morning that
spec is context engineering or specri
dev is sort of equivalent to context
engineering because the way that I think
of specri development is your
specifications become a control surface
for your codebase. Um, and that's
something that's been pretty uh a fairly
consistent throughine for the product
since we got started. So, uh, we'll talk
about that in just a second, but you've
heard it over and over today and
yesterday. But some of the challenges
with AI development, um, you have code
quality that is sort of all over the
place. You might get a golden patch one
day and just have terrible experience
the next. You've got limited control.
You're sort of begging the agent to do
something different. No, I meant this.
Da da da. and the agents do very well at
small tasks, but you are on the hook for
sort of breaking your task down to a
small, repeatable, and understandable
scope. Um, so we shipped spectriven dev.
We took about seven attempts to launch
spectriven development. We had various
implementations of this, some that we we
called, oh man, I think ephemeral specs,
we had hierarchical specs, we had um
TDDbased specs. Everything had to have
the word spec at the end. But at the end
of the day, we wanted you to be able to
interact with your system via natural
language. Uh you can interact with a
natural language representation of the
system component, module, whatever you
want to ship and the system will take
care of that. What we landed on is the
STD flow that we shipped today or
shipped a few months ago and we're
evolving today. Uh and that is that
effectively your specs represent the
state of the system you want to ship. So
previously vibe coding effectively
covered the implementation. It could
really cover anything. uh if you ask the
system to but we envision specs
effectively covering the full sequence
of the SDLC and we want to bring the
classical rigor for the software
development life cycle into AI
development. So what is spectriven
development in my mind uh I'll qualify
that um it's effectively a set of
artifacts and a structured workflow that
is what we launched Kira with and what
we're moving towards now is delivering
reproducible results. So the set of
artifacts we'll talk about first, but
effectively
when you use spectriven development in
Kirao today, we'll push you through a
workflow that produces a set of
artifacts that we suggest you commit
into your repo or you commit into
wherever you want it to be. Um,
effectively this is going to be
requirements design and tasks. Well,
I'll walk through sort of what each of
these is. If you were in uh Alex's talk
on backlog MD yesterday, there's going
to be a high overlap there. Um, but
effectively for requirements, I want to
be able to uh prompt my system. This is
just a this is not really a pitch for
Kuro. I'm just showing Kira spec mode.
Uh, let's build a CLI for meal tracking.
Da da da. Spit the thing out. Keep on
trucking. And Kuro is going to go off
and generate a requirements MD file for
me. And so this requirements file is our
interpretation of what the sort of PM in
your life would have done or if what
you're going to do if you're going to
break down work for other engineers on
your team. And effectively we give you a
set of basically an intro which is what
is the summary of the problem you gave
the customer what is the glossery of
terms. We'll talk a little bit a bit
more about that when we get towards
reproducible results. Uh and then a set
of requirements with related acceptance
criteria. So each of these AC's is now
addressable. We can reason about here
requirement 1.2 which is the meal
tracker shall CLI shall accept meal da
da da. Um but these requirements are
effectively user stories and then these
acceptance criteria we we represent in
ears format and ears is the easy
approach to requirement syntax uh
popularized by sort of other highly
governed industries but we took it
because it's a structured natural
language representation of what you are
saying to a system. So for people who
have worked in industries with
requirements engineering where that was
a thing um they might be familiar with
ears but it lets us use classic nonLM
tools on top of your requirements to
sort of reason about them. Again I'm
really excited to talk about that. Uh
that is a set of features that came out
with our GA on Monday. More about that a
little bit later. So that's your
requirements. The overview the glossery
the user stories or requirements and
then the acceptance criteria. Next up,
we'll talk a little bit about taking
that set of requirements and translating
it into a design. So, for the purposes
of the demo, I think I have not changed
my requirements at all. I gave the the
prompt was fairly straightforward. Give
me a meal tracking CLI. I want something
I can invoke. Maybe I asked for
something slightly different in the
requirements. I don't remember. Um, but
I Kira asks me, hey, are we happy with
the requirements or do you want to
iterate? In this case, I just said I'm
happy. Let's keep on trucking. And so
Kira is going to start generating a
design doc. Now this design doc is just
one template. Uh you are free to sort of
mutate it in any way you want. And the
template includes things like highle
system design modules interfaces uh
security concerns testing strategies and
the new addition as of Monday with our
GA release kuro 0.60 or 060 I should say
is properties. Um we'll talk a little
bit more about property testing towards
the end but that is effectively
identifying invariance in the system
which are what are the things that are
going to be true about the system no
matter what that if we can prove are met
will give you confidence that your
requirements are being met once you've
done once you're finished with
implementation. And in this case,
something else I did, and I might just
kind of rewind my video here briefly, is
uh we'll talk a little bit more about
this, but at the end, I think I said
something like, "Oh, I want to invoke
it." Yeah, you'll see the sample use
usage here was like node CLIJS
arguments. Um, and I said, "Looks good,
but I don't want to interact with node
CLI. I want to just have a named uh
command." So minor change but at any
point in time you're in this chatbased
environment. So you can chat with your
design docs, you can chat with your
requirements, you can chat with your
task lists. Um yeah, so at a high level
that's what the design is. It's going to
be the key technical details. It's going
to be interfaces. It's going to be
testing and security concerns. And
importantly, at least to me, it's highly
flexible because my opinion about what
matters in a design doc may be very
different than yours and yours and
yours. and we're going to be working on
things that are at different life
cycles. So I may care much more about
how a refactor project for example fits
into the larger ecosystem of the
codebase. Whereas if I'm doing green
field it's like skip over the details
just keep like let's move as fast as
possible. I only want to talk about
maybe the interface.
Last in our set of artifacts is the task
list. So curo's task list is the thing
that's closest to backlog empty. But
this is effectively um given a design we
want to break it down into tracer
bullets that can be implemented. each of
these tracers. Again, in the UI, I sort
of just say, "Yes, please go to tasks."
Um, and Kira is going to shepherd me
through this workflow. And these I
really should have should not have
scrolled that much while I was recording
this. But, um, it's [snorts] going to
give me a set of tasks potentially
nested and potentially deeply nested,
though we sort of disincentivize that
with the agent. uh which are written uh
they're effectively the equivalent of a
Jira or of a you know a sauna task or
whatever that I would give to an
engineer and they are uh human readable
and they tie really crisply back to a
requirement that is being solved by
these tasks. There's not a ton that's
actually super special about the task
breakdown. Some things we've done since
launch is we give you like optional
tasks. So if you don't want to add let's
say you're doing something closer to
vibe but you want to review design docs
as you go we would give you
like you could do MVP mode I think is
what we call it where we just don't
generate unit tests if you don't want if
you want to skip that. Uh additionally
with the addition of property tests we
now allow you to skip that as well. Uh
since property tests can be expensive at
least in implementation time although
they give you a lot of confidence in
what you're shipping. So that's kind of
the first um tent pole I'd say for what
I consider spectriven development to be.
The second is the structured workflow.
Um and then this is what's effectively
different. I've seen a lot of talks in
the last 36 hours from people to say you
know I do this and I do this and like I
go through things this way and
ultimately what I want to do for you is
[snorts] to make sure your tools do that
on your behalf and you don't have to be
an expert operator to have good results
out of your tools today. So this is kind
of a silly diagram, but effectively the
workflow we just walked through is a
very simple example. It's a three nodes
in a graph and at each node you can
always hop to this like iteration loop
and go back. Now what's not documented
is the fact that you're in a very
flexible system. At any point in time
you can just hop back and start tweaking
requirements, tweaking design, tweaking
tasks, whatever. Um so we do try to keep
things very flexible. We don't want to
be too rigid but we do want to move the
LLM and the agent itself I should say
through this structured workflow on your
behalf. Um, and then finally, this is
the thing I'm the most excited about is
the reproducible results. So, there's I
think two things we're doing as of this
release on Monday, uh, 0.6.0. One is we
reason over the requirements you provide
to the system to search for ambiguity. I
don't know that we surface these visibly
yet, although more to come. Uh, but we
will ask you questions to resolve
ambiguity in your requirements layer.
So, let's just say um in the example guy
shared this morning, he's got a button.
Uh if the system finds that you have
maybe gone through and built a bunch of
buttons and you're saying, "I want a
blue button or I just want a button and
it doesn't know if you want it to be um
like an accept or a secondary or an
alert or whatever." Um that's kind of a
trivial example, but you could come in
and the system would say, "Hey, this is
actually a fairly ambiguous requirement.
We have some automated reasoning systems
we run in the back end to help you
define these things or identify these
things and then the agent will actually
help you winnow down that ambiguity. So
that's step one. Uh step two, we
highlight the critical decisions in the
design and we will circle with you until
we are happy with kind of we understand
those decisions. You've made a decision
or you've said I don't care agent flip a
coin. Keep moving. And then third is
that we break the work out into
bite-sized chunks. So this is really
trying to move the amount of work we're
asking the agent at any point in time
down to the smallest uh unit of work
that could be theoretically committed.
Uh on the Curo team specifically, we
spend a lot of time breaking well I
should say we have a standard where
you'll you'll create a commit for
example with your specs and then you'll
create a commit for effectively every
task produced so that we can review the
code peacemail even if it's not
committed like push peace meal they are
independent commits that'll be pushed
and now this is the new stuff we shipped
on Monday that we're really excited
about. So this is an example of an ears
style requirement. It's basically a
subject predicate. Um so we have that
dictionary I talked about in the
beginning. So we will define what the
traffic control system is, what the
control module is, what all these
different things that are sort of
properties of the system are. And so the
ears format allows me to say while
um condition the traffic control system
subject is operating um this is the
state the control module subject shall
predicate maintain the invariant that at
most one direction displays green. This
is a very simple English sentence that
describes sort of the correct behavior
of a traffic light. You should, no
matter what happens, any sequence of
events, any sequence of interrupts, any
sequence of state should only at most
one direction should display green.
We're okay if they're all red, but you
don't want two green. That's a huge
problem. So what Kira's done here is
it's parsed this out in your design into
a property which is a type of invariant
a safety invariant that says that at
most one green signal for any sequence
of operations and then kind of all those
things I just mentioned at every point
in time at most one direction should
have a green signal and crisply we say
this validates requirement 2.3 and now
like on the surface this is not super
useful this is me just sort of reframing
the requirement I already wrote but we
then go and depending Depending on your
library of choice, we'll pick a property
based testing framework. Um, I think for
Python, we use hypothesis. For node, it
would be fast check. Again, if you have
a preference, you can tell Kira to use
that instead. And same ears requirement
is on the left. We will produce a
property test on the right. So, another
quick show of hands. Has anybody here
done like written property based tests
used? Okay, we got one, two, uh, three
in the in the back. Um, [snorts]
super powerful, huge pain in the ass.
Um, getting these right, having stopping
conditions and bounding conditions that
work are difficult. It's like everyone
likes BDD until you have to use cucumber
and actually implement it. Um, I find
for most teams, the same thing happens
with property testing. At a high level,
the way to think about it though if
you're not familiar is that you
represent the test cases of your system
as
um a set of you effectively define the
input space which will be autodefined by
your test runner and then you define the
the test behavior. So uh you know for
all countable numbers when I add them
two of them together the result should
be the two of them added. That's a bad
example but um maybe when I double them
modulo 2 should equal zero. Um well I've
just decomposed the problem into sort of
my problem search space and the ver the
verification logic and then systems like
hypothesis for python or fast check or
whatever kind of your pbt library
closure spec is another one um you will
go through the process of identifying
sort of the universe of possible test
cases identifying edge cases and then
through a process called shrinking which
is effectively the secret sauce of any
library it will run a bunch of these
samples through and try to find a single
counter example because all really all
the test needs is a single counter
example to say your requirement is not
being met. If you cannot find one either
one your universe of possible test cases
is bad or two your test is poorly
written. But assuming those two things
are not true which there are uh patterns
to address them. uh at the point that
you have a passing property test and the
property is testing the right thing in
your system, you have high confidence
that what you have shipped in code is
what you said you were going to ship.
And that is important because this means
that if I say while the traffic control
system is operating the control module
shall maintain the invariant that at
most one direction displays green and I
prove that I now have a high degree of
confidence in the safety of the system
I'm shipping. This is one example, but
there is a lot of uh there are a lot of
properties um I should say a lot of
types of invariants. We have I think
seven classes of invariants we consider
in Curo of which there's safety and
timing and data correctness and things
like that. So this is I think the
biggest thing we shipped in the last few
weeks is this property based testing. Uh
it's very new, hot off the presses as of
Monday. If you haven't tried out Kira, I
invite you to try out Kira, give it a
shot and let us know what you think. But
I've left quite a few minutes here at
the end for questions.
Uh I'm so happy about property based
testing. I'm just going to install it
tomorrow and do all kinds of things with
it. Thank you. Um curious one thing is
you say you break work into bite-sized
chunks.
>> Do you also give the context enough? So
sized context to do that and plus
anywhere they need to look at. So the
way we treat context for task execution
today is that we provide the entire
context of the goal that is the design
and the full task list but we are that
is effectively provided as background
context along with all your sort of
rules and norms your agents MD whatever
steering files but the task provided to
the system is execute task x.y which is
make a system that does this do not
implement further tasks do not you know
go beyond the brief. So we provide the
full context of the goal but we are
saying which is effectively the same as
like me giving a junior developer on the
team let's read the technical design of
the system you're adding the I don't
know payments widget something like that
that's the way we're thinking about it
today. Um it's perhaps slightly naive
and something we could iterate on quite
a bit.
>> Um which models are you using and is
that user selectable? Uh and is there
any option for local models? no option
for local models. I'm very sorry. Um,
but the model is user selectable for
most things. Um, in this case, I think
in the demo video, I'm using auto, but
today we have Sonnet [snorts] 4,45,
Haiku 45,
uh, maybe a few Nova models, and I think
we're trying to get Quinn in as well.
Um, yeah.
>> Um, property based testing is new to me
as of a few minutes ago, so I'm very
happy for that. Um but
having read what it is
the problem space can sometimes be
really big presumably for complex
systems. So like how do models deal with
reasoning over trying to find the right
set of constraints so that your property
based testing is valid like do you run
into problems there kind of scaling that
paradigm
>> in some cases we do. Um for example just
I think this weekend um one of the PMs
testing out the product uh before launch
said hey my test ran for 8 minutes.
what's going on? It's like yes, that is
a problem. We should fix that. Um, it is
it is one of the key challenges with
property testing is that anytime you
have sort of generative input, your
library of choice will actually have a
significant influence on the performance
of the system. But so that uh shrinking
of the problem space and definition of
the problem space need to go really
crisply handinand in order to have
success. So I'm going to say there's no
like panacea here. Uh probably we're
going to go through a little bit of a
learning period with this feature now
rolling out to many many more users, not
the hundred or so we've tested it with
in the past, but um if you've got
feedback, please reach out to us on
GitHub or Discord. Yeah.
>> Oh, okay.
Um is it possible to customize how the
specs are created? like meaning if I
wanted the ko to call some tools to
gather more relevant context before he
starts generating the specs is it
possible to do that or like
>> oh totally yeah yeah so I've given this
talk a few times in the past so I'm
giving it later this week as well around
um using for example MCP is a good
example because it's very easy to
rationalize but let's say um I actually
have a a killer product team they've
defined all of our goals and things in a
sauna and I don't want to copy things
into Kira I can just hook up to on MCP
and say like read all the tasks assigned
to me, rationalize this into one or more
projects and generate a specs for spec
for it or for them. Uh you can do that.
You can use specs during task execution,
I'm sorry, MCP or whatever. Um, that
kind of comes back to the thing I
mentioned a fair bit earlier, which is I
want the system to be highly flexible
for you as a user, which is that not
just that the structure is flexible and
you can kind of jump to wherever in the
workflow you want to revisit, um, but
also that you can change the the design
doc structure. You can change the task
list structure. Task list is a little
weird because we have highlighting on
stuff and checkboxes exist for certain
patterns, but uh, in general, you can
still do whatever you want. Um we are
just recommending that this is sort of
the best starting point.
>> Okay, we got one question online and
I'll take this gentleman at the front as
well. So question from uh AI native dev
discord. Uh how do you evolve specs or
design over time? So say that I want to
change a feature shipped months ago. Do
I start from a new spec? Do I take the
previous spec and change it?
>> Yeah. Um this is I think everybody who
ask is going to have a slightly
different opinion. My recommendation and
what I do on my team and suggest my team
does as well is that if I'm mutating
something that exists, I go and mutate
an existing spec. Let [clears throat] me
see if I can actually just jump out to
uh Curo for a moment. So, this is uh my
hero. Let me use a light mode.
That's not a light mode. I am going to
apologize for whatever I just did. Um,
so here's an example of the cure
extension. This is where a lot of our
code is. You can see I'm playing around
with Tesla and trying to integrate some
of the grounding specs over there. But,
um, if I hop into we we delete specs
actually fairly aggressively when
they're more than a few weeks old. So,
you can see the specs that are actively
or have recently been worked on. Um but
let's just for example say I want to
talk through uh the message history
sanitizer which is a project we we have
such that if you get into an invalid
state at any point in time the system
will kick it out. I can easily dive in
here and say I want to add a new message
history sanitization rule such that um
messages with a Levenstein distance
uh too close
will be dduplicated.
Um and so in this case I'm going to
commit my PR which really has an
amendment to the requirements. It will
have an amendment or set of amendments
to the design and net new tasks that get
shipped out. Uh we don't have to watch
the whole thing play here, but it's
going to go and find all of my specs.
It's going to read through relevant
specs, probably find the message
dduplicator one or sanitizer one, I
should say, and then go in and mutate
them. And instead of me shipping three
big docs to my team for review, we will
be talking about really diffs, which is
what we are working on here. Yeah. So,
in this case, it's read the existing
artifacts and it'll keep on trucking.
>> Awesome. Got time just for one more.
Also big shout out. Hello Macy. Um
sorry.
>> Thank you. Uh I was just curious if uh
like behind the scenes in Curo.
>> Does it kind of keep uh like a global
data of say data models and properties
of entities or does it actually every
time go and search out that what needs
to change?
>> Uh you mean like structurally in your
codebase or
>> Yeah. I I was curious like whe the
behind the scenes it has a map or a
model of how your objects and entities
relate to each other and you store that
or is every new spec going and mining
and figuring out where to add things and
what to change.
>> I would recommend you take a look at the
the slides Lada shared yesterday.
Effectively we do not do that
automatically for you but I think that
would be a reasonably easy thing for you
to do with memory or steering. Y um if
you haven't played with steering we have
I mean it's memory it's you know uh
claud's context whatever. Um, but yeah,
you can do a lot by just saying, "What
did you learn from this interaction?
What do you want to remember for next
time?" Put it in the steering dock so
that you can reload.
>> Cool. Thank you.
>> Yeah, thank you so much and thanks for
the patience. You were like second
person to raise your hand.
>> Thanks.
>> Awesome. Thank you very much, Al. And
yeah, Al is here. So, if you didn't get
the chance to ask a question, um, it's
lunch now, so don't let Al don't let Al
eat. Just keep asking him question after
question after question. Al, thank you
very much. Pleasure.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Heat.
Heat.